Let's talk about faders.
Actually, I need to
talk a lot about faders
because there's so
much you can do with them
and I've received a ton
of questions about them.
So I'm splitting this up into a series
with more videos coming very soon.
For this series, just like
I did in my sequence videos,
I've made a capture presentation file
as well as a blackout
file that you can download
on your computer, either Mac or PC.
You don't need to download capture.
You can just download the file
and use it right away with your iPad.
As long as your iPad and the computer
running the capture presentation file
are on the same network.
We're gonna start off super simple,
just talking about all
the button options you have
for your faders.
Let's get into it.
Okay, here we are in the file.
You can see I already have a fader
for my main sequence
with some looks made.
We're gonna make two looks real quick.
I'm gonna come to my
groups, grab my bulbs,
set them to full and I'll
come to fixture controls
and make them really blue
and I will record a new look.
So I'll change this to sequence two now
and I'll call this
flash and that looks good.
And I'll select manual values only.
So I only save the manual
values in this new sequence
and I'll save.
I can see my values turn yellow,
which means they're controlled by a fader
that I don't have selected.
So I'll come up here to my main sequence
and switch over to the
flash sequence I just created.
Now I'm just going to
change these to be warmer.
So we have a warm flash
and I'll record again.
I'll do manual values only
and I'll call this look warm flash.
Okay, great.
And we'll save that.
So now if I go to my fader page,
I can see I have a
second sequence fader created.
At the bottom, I can see the buttons
that blackout already assigns
because blackout knows
this is a sequence fader.
It gives me a play and a back button.
You can see if I hit play here,
it'll cycle me through the two looks.
If I hit back, it'll
reverse me through the two looks.
You can see this is the
same for this other sequence.
So I go through chronologically
and I can go back
chronologically as well.
Okay, so let's take a look
at some of the other
buttons we can assign.
To assign a button to an empty space,
you can press and hold up top here
and you'll get the button type pop up.
You can also press and
hold on the fader itself
and assign the buttons in
the position you'd like.
For example, if we wanted
to get rid of the play button
and just switch it to none,
we could do that and then save.
And you can see this
is a now empty button.
I can come here and press and hold
and reassign it to play and save.
Okay, so what are the button types?
The first button type
is none, which is empty.
It doesn't do anything.
The next button type is flash.
And for flash, we get
three options, flash return,
flash on and flash off.
A flash button means
when you're holding it,
the fader goes to 100.
And when you let go,
the fader will return
to one of the states you've specified.
So if we do flash
return, the fader will return
to whatever state it was last in.
Let's test that out.
So here I can see the
fader is at 100 and off.
If I flash and let go,
it returns to that state.
If I double tap to toggle it
on and move it to the middle,
if I flash, it'll go to 100 and I let go,
it returns on and to the middle.
If I double tap to turn it off
and I flash and I let
go, you'll see it returns
to that state as well.
If I press and hold here
and go into my flash settings
by clicking on it and
change it to flash on,
as you can see, the
fader is off right now.
But if I flash it and
let go, it stays on.
Flash stays on.
If I press and hold and click my flash
and change it to flash off and save,
if I turn it on and
flash it, it will turn off.
Let's look at temp.
Temp stands for temporary and allows you
to set specific timings for your fader.
I'll keep it on auto for now and save.
And you can see, if I
start the fader at zero
and hold temp, it will
come up for one second.
And when I let go, it'll
go down for one second.
You can adjust these
settings in the temp settings.
If I click here, you can
see my uptime is one second,
my downtime is one second,
and it has no wait time
before transitioning down.
If you switched this to
manual, you'll have to tap again
to send the fader back down.
So if I save that now and
I temp it up, it goes up.
If I tap it again, it'll go down.
Tap up, tap again, it goes down.
That's temp.
Of course, you can assign
these to any times you'd like.
Toggle does the same thing
as double tapping the fader.
It either turns it on or
off depending on what state
it was last in.
If I save that, you can
see it's off right now
because it's grayed out.
If I hit toggle, it turns on.
If I hit toggle again, it turns off.
Toggle on, toggle off.
I'll skip black for now
to say that on and off
do exactly what you expect.
I'll set one button on and
I'll set this top button to off.
And now if I save this
and turn the fader on,
it'll turn on and I can
use off to turn it off.
Okay, let's look at black now.
I'll change this off to a black.
Black is the reverse of flash.
So while you're holding it,
the fader will go to zero.
And when you let go, it will release.
So here I'll send the fader to 100
and then hold the black button.
It goes down.
When I let go, it releases back.
Next is selfix.
selfix stands for select fixtures
and it will just select via command line
all the fixtures that
have data within that fader.
And this works for all types of faders.
Let's try it out.
I'll save this as selfix.
I'll clear my command line.
And then if I click this button,
you can see in the bottom,
it will select all my bulbs.
If I press and hold on this sequence
and add a selfix button,
you can see if I click selfix,
it will also add all the
fixtures in that sequence.
This is a super helpful
button to have on your hardware,
like a stream deck or keyboard,
because in your main
sequence, I can just hit selfix
and then use the master scroll wheel
to dim everything up or down.
I'll hit selfix here.
And then I can be in my fixture page
and use the master scroll
wheel to dim everything down
or dim everything up.
Super awesome.
Let's pick a new button.
Next we have macro,
which is not yet implemented,
but that will allow you to set a macro
to trigger from this button.
Next we have play and back.
As we saw before, these are auto assigned
on every sequence fader.
Of course you can change them,
but they play through
looks with respect to timing.
I'll double tap looks to
give my sequence some timing.
And then coming back to my fader page,
I can see the timing
activates when I hit play.
If you want your sequence to
use timing when you go back,
you can change this in blackout settings
by toggling default back
button behavior to look timing.
Next, we have the fast
back and fast forward buttons.
These are just like playing back,
except they ignore look timing.
These will allow you to
quickly go through your looks
while ignoring any timing you've set.
Top will take you to your
first look in the sequence.
Let's take a look at that.
Here I'm on my last look.
If I select top, I'll
go back to my first look
with respect to timing.
I'll change top to go to,
and go to allows you to
pick which look you're in
from a list.
I'll tap go to, and now I
can pick between any look
and go to them with
respect to look timing.
Last is select.
I'll put select on both sequences
and select just allows me
to switch between sequences.
Right now, if I go to my fixture page,
I can see I'm in my main sequence.
If I go to my fader page and
now select this bar up here
indicates which sequence is selected.
If I select sequence two
here, this bar changes.
And if I come out here, I can
see I'm now in that sequence.
Again, this is
another really useful button
to have mapped to hardware.
So if you have a bunch
of different sequences
and you need to update one,
you can select that
sequence and then update.
If I come to this fader
three and load a fixture
and select an empty button,
you'll see you're given just the options
that apply to a fixture fader.
So that's a bit of a speed
run of all the fader buttons.
Hope that was helpful.
In upcoming videos, we'll look at the
entire fader page UI,
the settings in the fader configuration,
and of course the fader priorities.
Let me know in the comments
what you wanna see more of,
and I'll see you next time.